Weilin Cong

☑ congweilin95@gmail.com • CongWeilin ★ Website

Research Scientist at Meta AI. Research focuses on both the fundamental machine learning problems on graph-structured data (including optimization, generalization, and expressive power) and model architecture design. Published as first author in the top-tier ML and AI conferences including NeurIPS, KDD, ICLR, AISTATS, and SDM.

Experience

Meta Al

Research Scientist at Ranking & Foundational AI Team

Sunnyvale, CA, United States

Oct 2023 - Present

Pennsylvania State University

Graduate Assistant

- CSE 597 Large-scale Machine Learning TA

- D.A.T.A. Lab RA (Spring & Summer Semester)

State College, PA, United States

Jan 2018–Present

Amazon AWS AI

Applied Research intern at DGL & GraphStorm Team

Santa Clara, CA, United States

May 2023 - Sec 2023

Meta Al

Research intern at AI for Business Team

Menlo Park, CA, United States

May 2022 - Aug 2022

Facebook AI Applied Research

Research intern at Al Platform Team

Remote, United States
Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

China Mobile Research Institute

Deep Learning Software Engineer

Mobile face recognition application development.

Beijing, China Sep 2016 - Jun 2017

Education

Pennsylvania State University

Ph.D. (changed degree from M.S.) in Computer Science Engineering

State College, PA *Aug 2020 - Present*

Pennsylvania State University

M.S. in Computer Science Engineering

State College, PA Aug 2017 - Aug 2020

Beijing Institute of Technology

B.S. in Computer Science

Beijing, China Sep 2013 - Jun 2017

Most Recent Research Projects

Graph Representation Unlearning (AISTATS23)

Dec 2021 - Present

- We propose algorithms to efficiently remove the effect of a set of nodes on the pre-trained GNN model.
- Algorithm GraphEditor: We first formulate GNNs as an alternative problem with closed-form solution, then we can edit the weight parameters based on the change of graph structure. Paper
- Algorithm Projector: Based on our observation that the linear GNN's weight parameters (trained with logistic regression) are in the span of all node features, we propose to unlearn by projecting the original weight parameters into a subspace that is irrelevant to the deleted node features. The paper is accepted by AISTAT23 with very high rating. Paper

Dynamic/Temporal Graph Learning (SDM23, ICLR23-Oral)

Jun 2021 - Present

- Propose a Transformer-based dynamic graph learning method named Dynamic Graph Transformer (DGT). To improve the generalization ability, we introduce two complementary self-supervised pre-training tasks

- and show that jointly optimizing the two pre-training tasks results in a smaller Bayesian error rate via an information-theoretic analysis. We also propose a temporal-union graph structure and a target-context node sampling strategy for an efficient and scalable training. This work is accepted by SDM23. Paper
- We propose a conceptually and technically simple architecture that consists of three components: (1) a link-encoder that is only based on multi-layer perceptrons (MLP) to summarize the information from temporal links, (2) a node-encoder that is only based on neighbor mean-pooling to summarize node information, and (3) an MLP-based link classifier that performs link prediction based on the outputs of the encoders. Despite its simplicity, our proposal attains an outstanding performance on temporal link prediction benchmarks with faster convergence and better generalization performance. This work is accepted by ICLR as Oral paper (notable-top-5% paper). Paper

Distributed GNN Training (ICLR22)

Dec 2020 - Oct 2021

- Propose a communication-efficient distributed GNN training technique. Provide theoritical analysis on the convergence of the proposed distributed GNN training method, and shows its benefit over naively parameter average type of methods. Paper
- Understand Performance Degradation in Deeper GNN (NeurIPS21)
 Dec 2020 Jun 2020
 - Reveal the discrepancy between the theoretical understanding of over-smoothing and the practical capabilities of GCNs. Analyze the generalization capability of GCNs, and show that the training strategies to achieve high training accuracy significantly deteriorate the generalization capability of GCNs. Propose a decoupled architecture that enjoys a provable better expressive and generalization power. Paper
- o Minimal Variance Sampling Graph Neural Networks (KDD20)

Aug 2019 - Fed 2020

- Propose a decoupled variance reduction strategy that employs gradient information to adaptive sample nodes with minimal variance, while explicitly reducing the variance introduced by node embedding approximation. Accepted as a full paper by KDD20 research track. Paper
- Efficient Training Graph Neural Network by Lazy Sampling (NeurIPS20)
 Apr 2020 Oct 2020
 - Propose a framework that efficiently train GCN by lazy sampling, i.e., sampling periodically and effectively recycle the sampled nodes to mitigate data preparation overhead. The proposed framework enjoys superior speedup without compromising the accuracy. Accepted by NeuralPS20. Paper
- o Encrypted Rich-data Steganography Using GAN (MiseML20)

Aug 2019 - Aug 2020

- Propose an end-to-end generative adversarial network model to encode data types of different modalities,
 e.g., text, audio and image, and is able to hide message deeply into a cover image without being detected and decoded by a third-party adversary who is not given permission to access the message. Paper.
- Doubly Variance Reduced Graph Neural Networks

Aug 2019 - May 2022

Provide the first convergence analysis of sampling-based GCN training under weak assumptions. Propose
and analyze a general doubly variance reduction schema that can accelerate any sampling-based GCN
training method under the memory budget for GCN training. Paper is under submission. Paper

Technical and Personal skills

Related Fields: Machine Learning Engineering, Theoretical Machine Learning

Programming Languages: Python Machine Learning Tools: PyTorch